<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog</id>
    <title>Hi, I am Idrish laxmidhar. Blog</title>
    <updated>2025-03-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Hi, I am Idrish laxmidhar. Blog</subtitle>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[AI concepts for Tech Professionals]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals"/>
        <updated>2025-03-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="artificial-intelligence">Artificial Intelligence<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#artificial-intelligence" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Artificial Intelligence" title="Direct link to Artificial Intelligence">​</a></h2>
<p>AI is a vast field focused on creating intelligent systems that can perform tasks usually requiring human intelligence, such as perception, reasoning, and decision-making. It encompasses a range of techniques and approaches, including machine learning, deep learning, and generative AI.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="machine-learning-ml">Machine Learning (ML)<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#machine-learning-ml" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Machine Learning (ML)" title="Direct link to Machine Learning (ML)">​</a></h2>
<p>ML is a subset of AI focused on developing methods that enable machines to learn from data and enhance their performance on specific tasks. It is commonly considered the simplest form of AI.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="neural-networks">Neural Networks<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#neural-networks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Neural Networks" title="Direct link to Neural Networks">​</a></h2>
<p>A neural network is a computational model inspired by the human brain, consisting of interconnected layers of nodes or neurons that process and transform data through learned patterns and weights. It is commonly used in machine learning to recognize complex patterns, make predictions and solve tasks by training on large datasets.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="deep-learning">Deep Learning<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#deep-learning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Deep Learning" title="Direct link to Deep Learning">​</a></h2>
<p>Deep learning is subset of machine learning that utilizes multi-layered neural networks to automatically learn and extract features from large datasets. These deep network can model complex patterns and perform tasks such as image and speech recognition with high accuracy by heirarchically processing data through multiple layers.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="computer-visiion">Computer visiion<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#computer-visiion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Computer visiion" title="Direct link to Computer visiion">​</a></h2>
<p>Computer vision is a field of artificial intelligence that enables computers to interpret and understand visual information from the world, such as images and videos. It involves the use of algorithms and models to analyze and make decisions based on visual data, often mimicking human visual perception and cognition.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="natural-language-processing-nlp">Natural Language processing (NLP)<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#natural-language-processing-nlp" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Natural Language processing (NLP)" title="Direct link to Natural Language processing (NLP)">​</a></h2>
<p>Natural langulage processing (NLP) is a branch of artificial intelligence that allows computers to understand and interact with human language. It involves tasks like translating text, analyzing sentiment, and summarizing information by processing and interpreting language data.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ai-model">AI Model<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#ai-model" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AI Model" title="Direct link to AI Model">​</a></h2>
<p>An AI model is a computational algorithm trained on data to perform specific tasks, such as classifiction, prediction, or pattern recognition. It learns from examples in training data, adjusting its parameters to improve its accuracy, and then applies this learned knowledge to make informed decisions or predictions on new, unseen data.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ml-algorithm">ML Algorithm<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#ml-algorithm" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ML Algorithm" title="Direct link to ML Algorithm">​</a></h2>
<p>An ML Algorithm is a set of procedueres used to analayze data and make predictions or decisions based on patterns and insights. It adjusts its approach by learning from data, improving its accuracy over time through iteravtive training.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ai-model-training">AI Model Training<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#ai-model-training" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AI Model Training" title="Direct link to AI Model Training">​</a></h2>
<p>AI model training is the process of teaching a model to make accurate predictions or decisions by feeding it large amounts of data, adjusting its parameters through iterative learning, and optimizing its performance based on feedback and error rates.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ai-inferencing">AI inferencing<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#ai-inferencing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AI inferencing" title="Direct link to AI inferencing">​</a></h2>
<p>AI inferencing is the process of applying a trained AI model to new data to generate predictions or decisions based on the patterns and knowledge it has learned. It involves using the model's learned parameters to analyze the input and produce outputs in real-time or on-demand.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="model-fairness">Model fairness<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#model-fairness" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Model fairness" title="Direct link to Model fairness">​</a></h2>
<p>AI model fairness refers to the principle of ensuring that a model's predictions or decisions do not disproportionately disadvantage or bias any particular group or individual, promoting equitble outcomes.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="model-fit">Model fit<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#model-fit" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Model fit" title="Direct link to Model fit">​</a></h2>
<p>Model fit describes how well a model's predictions match the actual data it was trained on, indicating its accuracy and effectiveness in capturing the underlying patterns.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="large-language-model-llm">Large Language Model (LLM)<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#large-language-model-llm" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Large Language Model (LLM)" title="Direct link to Large Language Model (LLM)">​</a></h2>
<p>A Large language model (LLM) is an AI model designed to understand and generate human-like text based on vast amounts of data. It uses advanced algorithms to process and respond to language, enabling tasks like text generation, translation, and question-answering.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="machine-learning-workflow">Machine Learning Workflow<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#machine-learning-workflow" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Machine Learning Workflow" title="Direct link to Machine Learning Workflow">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Identifying appropriate data is one of the most important aspects of ML workflow.</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="labeled-data">Labeled Data<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#labeled-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Labeled Data" title="Direct link to Labeled Data">​</a></h4>
<p>Labeled data in AI refers to data that has been annotated with specific tags or categories, providing a reference for training models. This annoated information helps the model learn to identify patterns and make accurate predictions based on the labeled examples.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="unlabeled-data">Unlabeled Data<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#unlabeled-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Unlabeled Data" title="Direct link to Unlabeled Data">​</a></h4>
<p>Unlabled data in AI refers to data that lacks predefined tags or categories, meaning it has not been annoated with specific information. This type of data is often used in unsupervised leanring, where models identify patterns and structures without predefined labels.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tabular-data">Tabular data<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#tabular-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tabular data" title="Direct link to Tabular data">​</a></h4>
<p>Tabular data in AI is structured information organized in rows and columns, resembling a spredsheet or database table. Each row typically represents a single record or observation, while each column contains specific attributes or features, making it easy to analyze and process for machine learning tasks.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="time-series-data">Time-Series data<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#time-series-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Time-Series data" title="Direct link to Time-Series data">​</a></h4>
<p>Time-series data in AI consists of observations collected sequentially over time, ofter at regular intervals. this type of data is used to analyze trends, patterns, and seasonal variations, making it valuable for tasks such as forecasting and anamoly detection. This data is oftern submitted by IoT devices.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="image-data">Image data<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#image-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Image data" title="Direct link to Image data">​</a></h4>
<p>Image data in AI refers to visual information represented as pixel matrics, capturing various features such as colors, shapes, and textures. This type of data is commonly used in computer vision tasks, including image classification, object detection, and facial recognition.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="strucured-text-data">Strucured text data<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#strucured-text-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Strucured text data" title="Direct link to Strucured text data">​</a></h4>
<p>Structured text data in AI refers to text that is organized in a predefined format, often with specific fields and tags, making it easy to analyze and process. Examples include data from forms, databases, or CSV files, where each entry has a consistent structure that facilitates tasks like information extraction and analysis.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="unstructured-text-data">Unstructured text data<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#unstructured-text-data" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Unstructured text data" title="Direct link to Unstructured text data">​</a></h4>
<p>Unstructured text data in AI refers to free-form text taht lacks a predefined structure, such as documents, social media posts, or emails. This type of data is more challenging to analyze, as it requires natural language processing techniques to extract insights, indentify patterns, and derive meaning from the content.</p>
<hr>
<ul>
<li>Select the ML Algorithm</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="linear-regression">Linear Regression<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#linear-regression" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Linear Regression" title="Direct link to Linear Regression">​</a></h4>
<p>Modeling between a dependent variable and multiple independent variables
Eg. Predict housing prices based on size, location and number of bedrooms.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="logistic-regression">Logistic Regression<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#logistic-regression" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Logistic Regression" title="Direct link to Logistic Regression">​</a></h4>
<p>Binary classification predicting the probability of an event occuring.
Eg. Email spam classification</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="k-nearest-neighbors-knn">K-Nearest Neighbors (KNN)<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#k-nearest-neighbors-knn" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to K-Nearest Neighbors (KNN)" title="Direct link to K-Nearest Neighbors (KNN)">​</a></h4>
<p>Classification of data points based on classification of neighbors.
Eg. Product recommendation based on user preferences.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="principal-component-analysis-pca">Principal component Analysis (PCA)<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#principal-component-analysis-pca" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Principal component Analysis (PCA)" title="Direct link to Principal component Analysis (PCA)">​</a></h4>
<p>Condensing data while retaining the most important features
Eg. facial recognition</p>
<hr>
<ul>
<li>Train the model on the data</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="supervised-learning">Supervised Learning<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#supervised-learning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Supervised Learning" title="Direct link to Supervised Learning">​</a></h4>
<p>Supervises learning is a machine learning approach where a model is trained on labeled data, using input-output pairs to learn the relationship between them. The model makes predictions on new, unseen data by applying the patterns it has learned from the training examples.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="unsupervised-learning">Unsupervised learning<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#unsupervised-learning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Unsupervised learning" title="Direct link to Unsupervised learning">​</a></h4>
<p>Unsupervised learning is a machine learning approach where a model is trained on unlabled data, aiming to identify patterns, structures, or groupings within the data without predefined output categories. It is commonly used for tasks such as clustering, dimensionality reduction, and anomaly detection, helping to uncover hidden relationships in  the data.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reinforcement-learning">Reinforcement Learning<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#reinforcement-learning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reinforcement Learning" title="Direct link to Reinforcement Learning">​</a></h4>
<p>Reinforcement learning is a machine learning approach where an agent learns to make decisions by interacting with an environment, receiving feedback in the form of rewards or penalties. The agent aims to maximize cumulative rewards over time by exploring different actions and learning from the consequences of its choices.</p>
<ul>
<li>Evaluate Model performance. Perform a series of tests to validate whether the model generates usable output</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="batch-inferencing">Batch inferencing<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#batch-inferencing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Batch inferencing" title="Direct link to Batch inferencing">​</a></h4>
<p>Batch inferencing is the process of making predictions or decisions on a large set of data at once, rather than individually processing each data point. This approach allows for efficient and scalable analysis by handling multiple inputs in a single operation. Batch inferencing is used when accuracy is more important than speed of response.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="real-time-inferencing">Real time inferencing<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#real-time-inferencing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Real time inferencing" title="Direct link to Real time inferencing">​</a></h4>
<p>Real-time inferencing is the process of making predictions or decisions on data instantly as it is received, enabling immediate responses. This approach is crucial for applications requiring quick, dynamic interaction, such as live video analysis or online recommendation systems. Self-driving cars use real-time inferencing while in motion.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="real-world-examples-of-ai-applications">Real World Examples of AI applications<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#real-world-examples-of-ai-applications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Real World Examples of AI applications" title="Direct link to Real World Examples of AI applications">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Computer Vision
Autonomous vehicles utilize computer vision to interpret and navigate their environment. They rely on a combination of sensors, cameras, and AI algorithms to perceive  the world around them.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>NLP Speech recognition
Virtual assistants leverage NLP and speech recognition to understand and respond to user queries in natural language. They allow for hands-free operation of devices, providing users with a seamless interaction experience.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Recommendation systems
E-commerce platforms employ recommendation systems to provide personalized shopping experiences for users. These systems analyze user behavior and preferences to suggest products that are most likely to be purchases.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Fraud detection
Financial institutions, including banks and credit card companies, employ fraud detection systems to identify and prevent fraudulent transactions in real-time. These systems use ML algorithms to analyze transaction data and flag suspicious activities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Forecasting
In supply chain management, accurate demand forecasting is crucial for ensuring products are available to meet customer demand while minimizing excess inventory costs. Companies use AI to analyze historical sales data and predict future demand.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="introduction-to-rag">Introduction to RAG<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#introduction-to-rag" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction to RAG" title="Direct link to Introduction to RAG">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Retrieval Augmented Generation - The process of augmenting LLM output by referencing a knowledge base that is outside the context of the LLM training sources</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="knowledge-base-option">knowledge base option<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#knowledge-base-option" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to knowledge base option" title="Direct link to knowledge base option">​</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Traditional Database or Indexing Syatem
Use a traditional database or an indexing system like Elasticsearch. Here, the documents are indexed based on keywords or phrases. the retreval process invovles searching these indices to identify documents that match the query terms, which can then be sent to the LLM for generating responses.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Vector Database
In this method, structured or unstructured data are split into chunks, then embedded into vectors using a model (often a transformer-based encoder). These vectors are then stored in a vecotr database that supports efficient similarity search. When a prompt is submitted, this database is searched first, using a vecotr representing the query. It then retrives the most relevant documents based on vector similarity, and adds this data to the prompt.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="rag-benefits">RAG Benefits<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#rag-benefits" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to RAG Benefits" title="Direct link to RAG Benefits">​</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Enhanced factuality and accuracy</li>
<li>LLM contextual relevance</li>
<li>Improved handling of specific verticals</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="rag-challenges">RAG Challenges<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ai-tech-professionals#rag-challenges" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to RAG Challenges" title="Direct link to RAG Challenges">​</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Pipeline complexity</li>
<li>Latency issues</li>
<li>Dependence on the quality of the Retrieval set</li>
<li>Resource Requirements</li>
<li>Difficulty in Tuning and maintenance</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="AI" term="AI"/>
        <category label="upskilling" term="upskilling"/>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The four principles of Great design by Robin Williams]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/great-design</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/great-design"/>
        <updated>2025-02-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What started as a curiosity turned into a desirable hobby. After having discovered Canva in 2022, I started taking insipiration from various designs in Canva and Pinterest and created simple graphics for Watsapp Status and Instagram. Having this on hands experience, it helped me understand how to make something attractive and eye catching within a limited space and with limited use of words.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What started as a curiosity turned into a desirable hobby. After having discovered Canva in 2022, I started taking insipiration from various designs in Canva and Pinterest and created simple graphics for Watsapp Status and Instagram. Having this on hands experience, it helped me understand how to make something attractive and eye catching within a limited space and with limited use of words.</p>
<p>I enjoy spending hours on canva, but at the same time, I have gained creative and valuable skills while doing it on hands.</p>
<p>I came across this course from Robin Williams about principles of Great design and it surely benefited me from my existing knowledge. The course is well structured and here are some of the important points taken from the course.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-principle-of-proximity">The principle of Proximity<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/great-design#the-principle-of-proximity" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The principle of Proximity" title="Direct link to The principle of Proximity">​</a></h2>
<p>Group related items together. Physical closeness implies a relationship.
Proximity does not mean that everything is close together - it means elements that are intellectually connected should be visually connected.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-principle-of-alignment">The principle of Alignment<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/great-design#the-principle-of-alignment" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The principle of Alignment" title="Direct link to The principle of Alignment">​</a></h2>
<p>Nothing should be placed on the page arbitrarily. Even item should have a visual connection with something else on the page.</p>
<ul>
<li>In life as well as in Design, alignment has a purpose.</li>
<li>Clean alignment can improve the communication of any piece of work. It presents a more professional appearance.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-principle-of-repetition">The principle of Repetition<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/great-design#the-principle-of-repetition" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The principle of Repetition" title="Direct link to The principle of Repetition">​</a></h2>
<p>Repeat some element of the design throughout the entire piece. This is a critical unifying factor.</p>
<ul>
<li>You already create consistency in your design work. Take elements of that consistency and push it - emphasize the consistency so it becomes a repetitive and unifying element of design.</li>
<li>Repetition helps to clarify information and provide structure.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-principle-of-contrast">The principle of Contrast<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/great-design#the-principle-of-contrast" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The principle of Contrast" title="Direct link to The principle of Contrast">​</a></h2>
<p>Contrast is what draws a reader's eye to the page in the first place. Contrast also provides clarity of information.</p>
<ul>
<li>One effect of contrast is that it pulls the reader's eye into the information, and one result is clearer communication.</li>
<li>Use contrast to clarify information as well as make the page more attractive.</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="software" term="software"/>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deciphering Polyfill.io Service vs. Polyfill.js]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/polyfill.js</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/polyfill.js"/>
        <updated>2024-07-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In light of recent events, there's been some confusion about the polyfill.io service and polyfill.js. This article aims to clarify the differences and address some concerns.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In light of recent events, there's been some confusion about the polyfill.io service and polyfill.js. This article aims to clarify the differences and address some concerns.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-polyfillio-incident">The Polyfill.io Incident<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/polyfill.js#the-polyfillio-incident" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Polyfill.io Incident" title="Direct link to The Polyfill.io Incident">​</a></h2>
<p>News recently surfaced about the polyfill.io service injecting malicious code into JavaScript assets fetched from their domain. <a href="https://dev.to/snyk/polyfill-supply-chain-attack-embeds-malware-in-javascript-cdn-assets-55d6" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">This article</a> provides a detailed account of the incident.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-polyfills">Understanding Polyfills<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/polyfill.js#understanding-polyfills" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding Polyfills" title="Direct link to Understanding Polyfills">​</a></h2>
<p>According to MDN, a polyfill is a code snippet, typically JavaScript on the web, that provides modern functionality on older browsers lacking native support. For instance, if you want to use the latest JavaScript APIs like array <code>filter</code> or <code>map</code>—supported by Chrome but not IE7—you'd need a polyfill to ensure seamless functionality.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-role-of-cdns">The Role of CDNs<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/polyfill.js#the-role-of-cdns" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Role of CDNs" title="Direct link to The Role of CDNs">​</a></h2>
<p>A Content Delivery Network (CDN) is a system of interconnected servers that accelerate webpage loading for data-heavy applications. Commonly used static assets like jQuery, AngularJS, React, and Bootstrap.css reside on CDNs. Web applications can directly use these assets, saving on network and storage costs while enhancing application performance.</p>
<p>When a user in Location X visits your web application, the static files needed are downloaded from the nearest CDN to Location X, reducing latency and improving performance.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-case-for-external-services">The Case for External Services<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/polyfill.js#the-case-for-external-services" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Case for External Services" title="Direct link to The Case for External Services">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://kentcdodds.com/blog/polyfill-as-needed-with-polyfill-service" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">This blog post</a> provides an excellent discussion on using polyfill as a service. The main argument is that shipping polyfills for every feature can lead to unnecessary downloads for users with modern browsers. This can negatively impact performance and user experience.
An external service can help by shipping only the relevant polyfills based on the requesting browser's user agent.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="angulars-polyfilljs">Angular's polyfill.js<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/polyfill.js#angulars-polyfilljs" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Angular's polyfill.js" title="Direct link to Angular's polyfill.js">​</a></h2>
<p>Angular's build system generates optimized, production-ready code files, including a file named polyfill.js. There's been confusion about whether this polyfill.js is related to the polyfill.io incident.
The answer is a resounding NO.</p>
<p>Angular's polyfill.js is a file generated by the Angular build system for polyfilling required functionalities. It doesn't use any of the polyfill.io services to generate this build file, unless you're using the service in your source code.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="software" term="software"/>
        <category label="experience" term="experience"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons in Software Simplification - From AngularJS to Vanilla JS]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/software-simplification</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/software-simplification"/>
        <updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[8 Years ago…]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>8 Years ago…</p>
<p>AngularJS was very popular library and talk of the town.</p>
<p>The Software product had a requirement of providing a search solution with display of tabular data / pagination etc. with some UI animation.</p>
<p>It was decided by the tech lead and the management to go with AngularJS and there could be various reasons for it, possibly:</p>
<ul>
<li>AngularJS was popular framework</li>
<li>Going forward all the new features in this software product had to be developed using AngularJS</li>
<li>It is always exciting to work on a new technology irrespective of figuring out if it actually is needed.</li>
</ul>
<p>This feature was released and praised, but over the years, there have been no instances of this library being used for any other features, reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Continued usage of the legacy framework, it being the obvious choice</li>
<li>The rising popularity of Angular2 over AngularJS causing lack of time and interest.</li>
<li>Lack of resources / technical skills in AngularJS</li>
</ul>
<p>So, this huge product had AngularJS as a low hanging fruit, used only for one single feature.</p>
<p>However, security fixes to AngularJS library were patched whenever available.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="transition-from-angularjs-to-vanilla-javascript">Transition from AngularJS to Vanilla JavaScript<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/software-simplification#transition-from-angularjs-to-vanilla-javascript" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Transition from AngularJS to Vanilla JavaScript" title="Direct link to Transition from AngularJS to Vanilla JavaScript">​</a></h3>
<p>Fast forward to today, and our feature remains, but the landscape has shifted.  AngularJS is officially deprecated and so we had to reevaluate our choice.</p>
<ul>
<li>AngularJS library is deprecated.</li>
<li>Security concerns from customers</li>
<li>In this entire product, AngularJS is just used for this one feature.</li>
</ul>
<p>We chose to use Vanilla JavaScript for various reasons, though the specifics are not relevant here.</p>
<p>When I began working on this feature, it became clear that Vanilla JavaScript could effortlessly provide the same functionality.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="over-engineering-and-unnecessary-complexity-in-the-original-code">Over-Engineering and Unnecessary Complexity in the Original Code<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/software-simplification#over-engineering-and-unnecessary-complexity-in-the-original-code" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Over-Engineering and Unnecessary Complexity in the Original Code" title="Direct link to Over-Engineering and Unnecessary Complexity in the Original Code">​</a></h3>
<p>After careful evaluation of the code, it appeared that this feature was over-engineered.</p>
<ul>
<li>I discovered unused or infrequently used library files, bootstrap files, and a templating engine library.</li>
<li>I believe these libraries were added with the assumption that they would be useful for developing new features in the future. However, this turned out not to be the case.</li>
<li>Naturally, no one wanted to work with this code again, so all the core library files were left untouched.</li>
<li>There were clear violations of the DRY (Don't Repeat Yourself) and KISS (Keep It Simple, Stupid) design principles, indicating areas for improvement.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="enter-the-era-of-simplification">Enter the era of simplification.<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/software-simplification#enter-the-era-of-simplification" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Enter the era of simplification." title="Direct link to Enter the era of simplification.">​</a></h3>
<p>Opting for vanilla JavaScript, we embarked on a journey to streamline our codebase and embrace the principles of DRY (Don't Repeat Yourself), KISS (Keep It Simple, Stupid), and YAGNI (You Ain't Gonna Need It).</p>
<p>The entire exercise of removing AngularJs involved the following steps:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reviewing and understanding the entire feature</li>
<li>Reading the AngularJS code and identifying areas for improvement</li>
<li>Rewriting the entire feature using vanilla JavaScript</li>
<li>Ensuring the transformation does not affect the user, as only the underlying technology is being changed, not the user experience.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-transformation-from-excessive-to-efficient-coding">The Transformation: From Excessive to Efficient Coding<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/software-simplification#the-transformation-from-excessive-to-efficient-coding" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Transformation: From Excessive to Efficient Coding" title="Direct link to The Transformation: From Excessive to Efficient Coding">​</a></h3>
<p>What began as an experiment turned into a revelation. With over 16K lines of unnecessary clutter stripped away, and under 1K lines of focused, purposeful addition, we emerged with a leaner, more efficient feature.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Simplification" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/KISS-410b328e4a730630052a4571fc1a6ac8.png" width="1200" height="1200" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The journey wasn't without its challenges, but it was immensely rewarding. We honed our skills, boosted our confidence, and left behind a codebase that is not just functional, but elegant and maintainable.</p>
<ul>
<li>Increased my confidence in working independently on a feature.</li>
<li>Enhanced my ability to read any framework code and convert it to vanilla JavaScript.</li>
<li>Deepened my understanding of vanilla JavaScript.</li>
<li>Refactored the code, making it more readable and maintainable.</li>
</ul>
<p>As we continue to evolve, let's remember the value of simplicity, the power of pragmatism, and the importance of continuous improvement.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="software" term="software"/>
        <category label="experience" term="experience"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[PR#458 - My Prodest PR yet!!!]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet"/>
        <updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this blog post, I am thrilled to share the story behind my proudest Pull Request (PR) yet. PR#458 wasn't just another contribution but a significant milestone in my journey as a software developer. It was a challenging task that pushed me to my limits, and in overcoming those challenges, I learned valuable lessons that have shaped my approach to coding.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this blog post, I am thrilled to share the story behind my proudest Pull Request (PR) yet. PR#458 wasn't just another contribution but a significant milestone in my journey as a software developer. It was a challenging task that pushed me to my limits, and in overcoming those challenges, I learned valuable lessons that have shaped my approach to coding.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="by-the-numbers">By the Numbers<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet#by-the-numbers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to By the Numbers" title="Direct link to By the Numbers">​</a></h2>
<p>Before we delve into the story, let's take a moment to appreciate the sheer scale of this Pull Request. It comprised nearly 10 individual commits, introduced close to 2,800 new lines of code, and astonishingly, resulted in the deletion or modification of over 314,400 lines across almost 1,000 files.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="history">History<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet#history" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to History" title="Direct link to History">​</a></h2>
<p>The project I worked on has a rich history spanning almost two decades, evolving from a Windows application to a browser-based web app with a diverse tech stack.
This enterprise application has made careers of many software engineers, which means this codebase had been touched by many software engineers.
With wide tech stack such as CPP, Java and Dojo framework on the UI, over the years, it accumulated tech debt, and my role primarily focused on UI enhancements and refactoring.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-need-for-a-change">The need for a change<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet#the-need-for-a-change" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The need for a change" title="Direct link to The need for a change">​</a></h2>
<p>The accumulation of tech debt prompted a thorough review of the codebase to identify areas for improvement:</p>
<ul>
<li>Removal of unused assets and code snippets.</li>
<li>Refactoring of legacy code to improve readability and maintainability.</li>
<li>Elimination of support for outdated browsers.</li>
<li>Streamlining of build scripts to remove unnecessary generated files.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="motivational-quotes">Motivational Quotes<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet#motivational-quotes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Motivational Quotes" title="Direct link to Motivational Quotes">​</a></h2>
<p>I came across a tweet from Elon Musk that resonated deeply with me: "Far better to delete code than add it." This philosophy encapsulates the essence of efficient software development. While striving for 100% optimized and performant code from day one may seem ideal, the reality is that codebases evolve over time, accumulating unnecessary complexities and redundancies.</p>
<p>Another quote I hold dear is, "Always leave the code better than you found it," attributed to Ward Cunningham. This mindset drove me to embark on a journey of code refactoring and deletion, particularly in a legacy codebase spanning two decades.</p>
<p>Given that we were at the onset of a new release cycle, it presented the perfect opportunity to implement these changes.
In the process, I identified several areas ripe for improvement:</p>
<ul>
<li>Eliminating unused styles and assets meticulously, even if they were part of the codebase for years.</li>
<li>Letting go of support for outdated browsers, such as IE6, as their usage dwindled over time.</li>
<li>Since our project utilized the Dojo framework, it came with its own set of theme files. I painstakingly sifted through these files, pinpointing and eliminating any redundant styles that were no longer in use.</li>
<li>Streamlining build scripts to remove unnecessary auto-generated files, optimizing the build process.</li>
</ul>
<p>These actions required patience and thorough unit testing at every stage to ensure they didn't impact existing functionality adversely. By adhering to these principles and embracing the challenge of improving legacy code, I not only enhanced the codebase's quality but also cultivated a mindset of continuous improvement in software development.</p>
<p>We diligently conducted unit tests at every stage to ensure that our changes didn't inadvertently impact any existing functionality.</p>
<p>In the end, this comprehensive cleanup effort not only improved the overall quality of our codebase but also positioned us for smoother development cycles in the future.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-result">The Result<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet#the-result" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Result" title="Direct link to The Result">​</a></h2>
<p>The PR was not only about code changes but also about personal growth:</p>
<ul>
<li>Increased confidence in tackling a codebase spanning two decades.</li>
<li>Improved code readability and maintainability.</li>
<li>Timely refactoring to prevent future tech debt.</li>
<li>Opened doors for new opportunities and stretch assignments.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="room-for-improvement">Room for improvement<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet#room-for-improvement" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Room for improvement" title="Direct link to Room for improvement">​</a></h2>
<p>While I'm incredibly proud of this PR, reflecting on it, there are areas where I could have refined my approach:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Learning Opportunity:</em> This PR provided me with a valuable opportunity to delve deep into the codebase, uncovering insights and learning valuable lessons along the way. It's crucial to leverage such opportunities for continuous growth and improvement.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Confidence Boost:</em> Deleting code can be daunting, especially when it seems to be functioning correctly. However, this experience reinforced my confidence in making impactful changes to enhance the codebase's quality and performance.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Enhanced Readability and Maintainability:</em> By eliminating unused code and improving overall code cleanliness, we not only optimized performance but also made future development efforts more efficient. Why burden ourselves with code that serves no purpose? Additionally, utilizing version control tools like Git and GitHub ensures that we can always reference previous versions if needed.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Doors to New Opportunities:</em> Although this PR focused on code cleanup rather than adding new features, it opened doors to exciting opportunities. It demonstrated my commitment to maintaining code quality and readiness to tackle tech debt, qualities that are highly valued in any development team.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>In hindsight, I could have further optimized my approach:</p>
<ul>
<li>Breaking down the tasks into smaller, more focused PRs could have facilitated smoother integration and minimized the risk of unintended side effects. This iterative approach would have allowed for more granular testing and validation over multiple production builds, ensuring a seamless transition.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/proudest-pr-yet#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, working on PR#458 was an enriching experience:</p>
<ul>
<li>Deepened my understanding of the codebase.</li>
<li>Boosted my confidence in refactoring and deletion.</li>
<li>Enhanced the overall quality of the codebase.</li>
<li>Presented new opportunities for professional growth and learning.</li>
<li>Overall, PR#458 represents not just a code contribution but a journey of growth, learning, and improvement.</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="software" term="software"/>
        <category label="experience" term="experience"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Reasons to enjoy working on Legacy code]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/working-with-legacy-code</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/working-with-legacy-code"/>
        <updated>2022-11-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Working on legacy code has its own advantages and in this post I want to talk about how I enjoy and appreciate working on code that is dated as old as 15+ years.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Working on legacy code has its own advantages and in this post I want to talk about how I enjoy and appreciate working on code that is dated as old as 15+ years.</p>
<p>You do not always get to start a project from scratch. Any software product usually evolves over time and ensuring that all the future developments are robust requires considerable efforts.</p>
<p>While I have worked on both new projects from scratch to legacy products and both have immense learning opportunities, I want to write about how I enjoyed working on Legacy code that was dated as old as 15+ years.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="1-code-is-poetry">1) Code is poetry<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/working-with-legacy-code#1-code-is-poetry" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1) Code is poetry" title="Direct link to 1) Code is poetry">​</a></h2>
<p>This is the most famous wordpress tagline to which I concur. I have had amazing time going through the existing code written over span of 15+ years.</p>
<p>With the developer friendly tools, it is easier to debug code, so learning about why a certain piece of code was written, you learn a lot about the philosophy of the software.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2-boosts-confidence">2) Boosts confidence<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/working-with-legacy-code#2-boosts-confidence" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2) Boosts confidence" title="Direct link to 2) Boosts confidence">​</a></h2>
<p>Learning to read someone else’s code and appreciating their thought process helps you make better decisions. It gives you confidence to go with the existing solution or challenge the existing solution. Either way, it benefits the software product overall.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="3-scope-of-improvement">3) Scope of improvement<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/working-with-legacy-code#3-scope-of-improvement" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3) Scope of improvement" title="Direct link to 3) Scope of improvement">​</a></h2>
<p>There is always the scope for improvement. I enjoyed creating Pull Requests to tackle code smells such as</p>
<ul>
<li>Removing code that was specifically written to support certain IE version</li>
<li>Refactoring functions</li>
<li>Removing inline styles</li>
<li>Separating the JS from HTML code</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="4-documentation">4) Documentation<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/working-with-legacy-code#4-documentation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4) Documentation" title="Direct link to 4) Documentation">​</a></h2>
<p>Complex software such as these that are evolved over 15 years of time have a lot of scope for documentation. Adding new comments is easy, but improving existing comments / documentation requires thorough understanding of the code.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="5-appreciation-for-knowledge-sharing">5) Appreciation for Knowledge sharing<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/working-with-legacy-code#5-appreciation-for-knowledge-sharing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5) Appreciation for Knowledge sharing" title="Direct link to 5) Appreciation for Knowledge sharing">​</a></h2>
<p>It is easy to complain about someone else’s code. However, I have enjoyed going through the history of the commits and the JIRA tickets dated 10 years from now and have appreciated the detailed documentation that the developers at the time wrote. It takes patience to dig through the history but it is worth the efforts.</p>
<p>I am thankful to detailed documentation I have, I am also responsible towards ensuring that all my commits have traceable JIRA tickets linked for anyone in the future.</p>
<p>To summarize</p>
<ul>
<li>Embrace the code, enjoy the learning.</li>
<li>Take up the opportunity to improve the code and take complete ownership.</li>
<li>Read and Contribute to the documentation as much as possible.</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="software" term="software"/>
        <category label="essays" term="essays"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone should learn UX]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux"/>
        <updated>2022-02-18T12:10:42.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[With technology, digitization and access of internet, things are moving ahead at rapid pace. I feel that User experience (UX) is the most valuable skill that everyone should possess.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With technology, digitization and access of internet, things are moving ahead at rapid pace. I feel that User experience (UX) is the most valuable skill that everyone should possess.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="history"><strong>History</strong><a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#history" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to history" title="Direct link to history">​</a></h3>
<p>In the early 2000’s, we had UI developer and Backend developer.</p>
<p>All the tech shops worked as follows.</p>
<p>UI developer would design a website in photoshop, then convert it to html pages.</p>
<p>Backend developer would take the pages developed by the UI developer and convert it to a functional web app with PHP as server side language and MYSQL as database.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-little-about-ux-in-my-own-words">A little about UX in my own words<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#a-little-about-ux-in-my-own-words" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A little about UX in my own words" title="Direct link to A little about UX in my own words">​</a></h3>
<p>With technology, digitization and everything on our fingertips, to innovate and build a product for the masses, we also need to evolve with time. If we have to consider the IT domain, we have experts in Front end, Back end and most importantly UX (User Experience).  There are many other important roles, but for this blog post, let’s focus on the UX role.</p>
<p>Photoshop is no longer even a choice when designing a web app. Photoshop is now back to its original use case i.e photo retouching.</p>
<p>To design and develop a web app, we have tools like Invision, Adobe XD, Figma etc. However, before we have identified how the app will look like, we have a dedicated team of UX (User Experience) experts who develop a prototype of the web app.</p>
<p>A UX Expert would design a flow of the web app considering the end user in mind. They would talk to the actual customer or identify a persona so that a user flow can be designed. This is a key criteria to ensure that the actual goal of creating a web app is fulfilled.</p>
<p>In our scenario of developing a digital product i.e. a Web application,  UX exert needs to primarily take care of two things</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>The user flow</strong></p>
<p><strong>For eg. Think of eCommerce app that let’s you buy books.</strong></p>
<p>There are various scenario’s that we need to consider here</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>A user knows what they want to buy</p>
<p>They search the book, add to cart and get it delivered.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A user is looking to gift a book</p>
<p>They need to search based on age, gender, author, genre of the book etc. etc. A lot of criteria come into picture, before actual buying happens.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A user wants to browse books and save them in Wishlist</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Actual web app</p>
<p>What I mean by this is, placing a button where a button needs to be present. There have been various studies on how a user views a web app on a desktop browser, how they interact on a mobile device etc.</p>
<ul>
<li>Let’s say that our eCommerce web app is entirely dependent on user’s search. This means that we need to keep the input search right on the top of the web page so that it is prominent.</li>
<li>Use of icons. We have standard icons for user, shopping cart etc. so the UX should know which icon should be shown next to a particular item.</li>
<li>Add to cart should be primary button. Proceed to pay should be a prominent button.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The idea of this entire exercise and involvement of a UX expert is that the entire experience of the web application, from landing on the web page to buying should be extremely easy to follow, it should be hassle free and the user should be able to perform their desired actions without anyone’s assistance.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-should-anyone-learn-ux-">Why should anyone learn UX ?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#why-should-anyone-learn-ux-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why should anyone learn UX ?" title="Direct link to Why should anyone learn UX ?">​</a></h3>
<p>UX is more than what we have summarized above. Perhaps I did not even do Justice to the amount of work an UX expert does. However, with above summary, I wanted to lay a premise so that we can proceed with why everyone should learn UX.</p>
<p>Just like an UX Expert looks for a persona (the aspect of someone's character that is presented to or perceived by others), let me first define who “anyone” here is, what is the persona that this blog post is targeted towards.</p>
<p>We could be anything and not limited to the below</p>
<ul>
<li>Some technical artisan (Full stack, Back End, Dev ops etc.)</li>
<li>A home maker</li>
<li>A business owner</li>
<li>A creative ninja (artist, craftsmen etc.)</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="consider-below-user-persona">Consider below user persona<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#consider-below-user-persona" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Consider below user persona" title="Direct link to Consider below user persona">​</a></h3>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="1-content-consumer">1) Content Consumer<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#1-content-consumer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1) Content Consumer" title="Direct link to 1) Content Consumer">​</a></h3>
<p>We live in the digital world. From watsapp video calls, to booking a travel ticket online, we interact with almost everything on our smart phone, smart watch or the TV. We create content and we consume content in and out, so we ourselves are heavy users of applications. If we had to book a travel ticket but after opening the app, we were not able to figure out how to login, imagine how frustrating it would be.  Would we visit a food deliver app if it could not identify our location and suggest some restaurant that is impossible to our reach ?</p>
<p>With that, I can easily assume that we being the consumers, are qualified to give suggestions on how a user experience should be.</p>
<p>So if we can put in little efforts and understand the basic nuances of the world of UX, we can be of great help towards making any application a rich application.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2-content-creators">2) Content creators<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#2-content-creators" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2) Content creators" title="Direct link to 2) Content creators">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>A business owner</strong> always looks out for graphic designers to create flyers for them so that their business can be advertised.</p>
<p><strong>A home maker</strong>, although not into business but would and should always look out to advertise their hobby. We are always honored to cook a meal for our family and friends. We put in all the heart into decorating it. Would we not want to show it to the world through our instagram or watsapp ?</p>
<p>Considering the above two eg. (A business owner and A home maker), what I am trying to convey is that everyone is a content creator. Everyone wishes to publish on their story a picture they are proud of.</p>
<p>If we know how to design beautiful and catchy images, we are sorted.</p>
<p>How does UX play a role here ?</p>
<p>An image that has no caption, a phone number that does not have a beautiful icon, would be less attractive and not so catchy. Similarly, using a lot of different font families, having multiple colors to a single word or even having a lot of text overlay on your image may not be attractive.</p>
<p>UX or User experience is something that everyone should have the knowledge. No, we do not want to be an expert but we surely want to know when to fill up that white space or when to show a caption on an image, so that we are able to make such tiny yet effective decisions.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lets-create-experiences">Let’s create Experiences.<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#lets-create-experiences" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Let’s create Experiences." title="Direct link to Let’s create Experiences.">​</a></h3>
<p>Photoshop was the de facto tool for every designer. Anyone who had a computer and photoshop could be a graphic designer. Times have changed.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Canva to the rescue. With internet connection and a smart device, everyone can create experiences. An innovator can easily create prototypes of their ideas, a home maker can play around and share their creativity and promote themselves. Applications like canva, Figma are super easy to use. However imagine the dilemma of not able to create content to your liking and not able to do it right. With some knowledge of UX, you know exactly what you want.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you are a professional, a backend developer or a front end developer, you have an idea and you need to validate it with a MVP (Minimal viable product), you are golden.</p>
<p>You have knowledge of UX, you can easily use CSS frameworks like bootstrap and create a minimal working prototype. You are not dependent and blocked because you cannot imagine how the user flow will be and you can concentrate on building your product.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Quick results and faster Validation of your product with the actual user base.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Stressing over User Experience?  When you have an idea but are blocked because of lack of knowledge of how the UX should be, you will never able to see what that idea could have turned into. We want to create a product, so should we stress over the quality ? We can always refine our product, but if we are not aware of the basics of UX, we would not only waste time but also not have confidence in our own idea.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="we-all-should-learn-ux">We all should learn UX<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/everyone-should-learn-ux#we-all-should-learn-ux" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to We all should learn UX" title="Direct link to We all should learn UX">​</a></h3>
<p>Not everyone can be a great designer or an UX expert, but we should at least be able to understand and contribute to user experience.</p>
<p>Everything is getting digital and we have to stay ahead of time, so why not invest our time learning a skill that we will be using, knowingly or unknowingly.</p>
<p>Have basic knowledge of UX will definitely help us in every aspect of our day to day life. We want a rich, delightful experience from whatever we consume. Why not give the same experience to whatever we create ?</p>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="learnings" term="learnings"/>
        <category label="essays" term="essays"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[First time attending a meetup - My Experience]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup"/>
        <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A group of individuals with common interest plan to meet to share their knowledge and network. This is my definition of a Meetup. I have read several blogs about meetup's but never attended any. I did not plan anything nor did I know about this meetup until a day before. It was just on the spur of the moment. I am glad, I attended this meetup and hence sharing my experience through this blog post.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A group of individuals with common interest plan to meet to share their knowledge and network. This is my definition of a Meetup. I have read several blogs about meetup's but never attended any. I did not plan anything nor did I know about this meetup until a day before. It was just on the spur of the moment. I am glad, I attended this meetup and hence sharing my experience through this blog post.</p>
<p>I have no clue what made me register on the meetup.com website. It was Friday evening, I was about to wrap up my daily office work. I pointed my browser to meetup.com and registered. The website popped at me a meetup that was happening on Saturday 05th of Oct 2019 from 10.00 AM to 12.00 PM. The host were sharing their experience about <b>React with Typescript == React on Steroids</b>. Interesting. I wanted to learn about it. Unfortunately, RSVP were closed. "I could always watch about such topic on YouTube", I thought.</p>
<p>Surprisingly, someone in the comment had mentioned that no need of RSVP, everyone is welcome. I did not have any excuse but attend.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-is-a-meetup">What is a Meetup?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup#what-is-a-meetup" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is a Meetup?" title="Direct link to What is a Meetup?">​</a></h2>
<p>Like minded individuals get together on a decided place at a particular time. They share knowledge and their experience on a particular topic. Technology related meetups are usually hosted by companies on their premises.
It is well proven fact that if you want to remember something that you have learned, the best way is to teach and share that knowledge.
In the technology domain, there are multiple ways of doing the same thing. The most optimized way is preferred. Thus, when well experienced individuals from different companies/domain get together to learn and share their knowledge, there is bound to have an amazing learning experience.</p>
<p>In a Meetup, we discuss, share, learn and unlearn.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Meetup" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/equal-experts-meetup-8bc518adb3a1c8afd8429f142612ce89.jpg" width="500" height="770" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience">My Experience<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup#my-experience" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My Experience" title="Direct link to My Experience">​</a></h2>
<p>The meetup was hosted by "Equal Experts". The topic of discussion was "React with Typescript == React on Steroids".  At first, I was sceptical about attending the meetup, but the moment I entered their premises, I was convinced. They had a very pleasant workspace, huge monitors and the projector and mic system were already in place. The speakers were ready. On time. I filled in my basic information and made myself comfortable to the nearest empty seat.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-best-part">The best part<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup#the-best-part" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The best part" title="Direct link to The best part">​</a></h2>
<p>The discussion. I could feel the sync between the topic and the questions that the participants asked related to the topic. It was streamlined by the organizers and everyone was heard. I believe the most important factor in a small group discussion is that everyone wants to be part of the discussion and be heard. We all want to contribute our knowledge and share our experiences. I guess, that is why story telling has its existence.</p>
<p>In the meetup, I found myself engrossed in the stories and experiences that were shared.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-i-learned">What I learned?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup#what-i-learned" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I learned?" title="Direct link to What I learned?">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Typescript is truly important in a large project which has multiple developers. Angular 2+ realized the importance of Typescript and took a leap towards it. React has an amazing community which provides @Type definitions for it.</li>
<li>Creating a custom type means you will have to write an interface. Despite of knowing this, I asked this question to reconfirm my knowledge. Let's say you want to create a custom type <code>Accounts</code>, you would be creating an interface which would have all the properties that you need in that custom type.</li>
<li>You can have a union of two Types associated to an object. Let's say there is an <code>Employee</code> object that needs to have two custom types, i.e <code>Accounts</code> and <code>AccountNumber</code>. We can use the <code>&amp;</code> operator to allow both the types assigned to <code>Employee</code>. I had earlier experienced this situation where some property were not present in my interface definition and I was confused whether edit the existing interface or create a new interface including the new properties. So I could relate the importance of the <code>&amp;</code> operator.</li>
<li>Typescript is just a icing on the cake. It is used during the development time to help developer write error free code. The IDE intelli-sense would shout at you with the red squiglly lines in case you introduced any issues in the code. When the code is build and pushed to production, all your typescript code is scrapped out. Thus, it is important to note that you should include your TypeScript in the dev-dependencies in the package.json file.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="example">Example<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup#example" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Example" title="Direct link to Example">​</a></h2>
<p>Let us consider below example. We are creating an interface which means we are creating a custom type. So <code>SquareConfig</code> is a type which will have two properties <code>color</code> and <code>width</code>.  <code>color</code> will always be of type <code>string</code> and <code>width</code> will always be of type <code>number</code>. The <code>?</code> after the property name means that these are optional properties.</p>
<div class="language-javascript codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-javascript codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#393A34;background-color:#f6f8fa"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token keyword" style="color:#00009f">interface</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token class-name">SquareConfig</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    color</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">?</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> string</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    width</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">?</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> number</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div>
<p>After we create our custom type, we use it in below function. So the <code>createSquare</code> function accepts one parameter/argument <code>config</code> and it's type should be <code>SquareConfig</code>.
Now notice the code after the closing bracket of function name, before the <code>{</code> bracket, i.e <code>: {color: string, area: number}</code>. This represents the return type of the function. What it means that the function should always return an object which will have a property <code>color</code> of type <code>string</code> and <code>area</code> which is of type <code>number</code>.</p>
<div class="language-javascript codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-javascript codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#393A34;background-color:#f6f8fa"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token keyword" style="color:#00009f">function</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token function" style="color:#d73a49">createSquare</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">(</span><span class="token parameter literal-property property" style="color:#36acaa">config</span><span class="token parameter operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token parameter"> </span><span class="token parameter maybe-class-name">SquareConfig</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">)</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token literal-property property" style="color:#36acaa">color</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> string</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"> area</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> number</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token keyword" style="color:#00009f">let</span><span class="token plain"> newSquare </span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token literal-property property" style="color:#36acaa">color</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"white"</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token literal-property property" style="color:#36acaa">area</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token number" style="color:#36acaa">100</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token keyword control-flow" style="color:#00009f">if</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">(</span><span class="token plain">config</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token property-access">color</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">)</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        newSquare</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token property-access">color</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token plain"> config</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token property-access">color</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token keyword control-flow" style="color:#00009f">if</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">(</span><span class="token plain">config</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token property-access">width</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">)</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">        newSquare</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token property-access">area</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token plain"> config</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token property-access">width</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">*</span><span class="token plain"> config</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">.</span><span class="token property-access">width</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">    </span><span class="token keyword control-flow" style="color:#00009f">return</span><span class="token plain"> newSquare</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token keyword" style="color:#00009f">let</span><span class="token plain"> mySquare </span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token function" style="color:#d73a49">createSquare</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">(</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">{</span><span class="token literal-property property" style="color:#36acaa">color</span><span class="token operator" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"black"</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">}</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">;</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div>
<p>From above example we learn that, when defining a function we can construct in such a way that helps us identify the type of parameter and its return type. This in turn helps us during development time. So for example, let's say another developer uses this function somewhere in their code. When writing the code, they will be prompted by the intellisense that the arguments should be of type <code>SqaureConfig</code>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/attending-meetup#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>YouTube will always be there with amazing resources. But Meetup takes the learning experience one step above. First of all, getting out of your bed on a Saturday, breaking the comfort zone of meeting unknown people is itself a huge leap. Next comes, how good a listener you are. Do you get distracted? Can you relate the topics under discussion with your current work? Do you have any questions? How well you frame your questions? When to ask your doubts? All this may sound a lot of work, but trust me, over time it will be helpful. I am sure, it will definitely help me.</p>
<p>Apart from personal development, I enjoyed the culture. The host had ordered Pizza for everyone and that is when we networked. We shared our experiences in the project with the current technology. There were open questions that everyone opinionated about. All in all, it was time well spent.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="meetup" term="meetup"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The minimalist phone]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone"/>
        <updated>2019-10-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Smartphone's and in turn social media plays a very important role in our life, without which we would be stranded. Right? To a certain extent it is the truth. We use social media because we want to be connected. But we forget the toll it takes on our life through its continuous usage. In this post, I go through my journey from a social media addict to being a social media ghost.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Smartphone's and in turn social media plays a very important role in our life, without which we would be stranded. Right? To a certain extent it is the truth. We use social media because we want to be connected. But we forget the toll it takes on our life through its continuous usage. In this post, I go through my journey from a social media addict to being a social media ghost.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-it-all-started">How it all started<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#how-it-all-started" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How it all started" title="Direct link to How it all started">​</a></h2>
<p>With the invention of internet and its ease of availability, the youth were excited. We could explore various online platforms. It all started with Orkut. Then we learned about free blogging platforms like blogger. While social media was in rising, to think of it now, I realize that the craze was more towards the acceptance. What do I mean by acceptance? Every time we logged in to our internet (Yes, the dial-up days) and visited our profiles, we wanted to know how many scraps (Orkut) we got and who commented on our blog posts. Creating content was fun back then. We would feel connected and accepted to someone unknown.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-smart-phone-era">The Smart Phone era<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#the-smart-phone-era" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Smart Phone era" title="Direct link to The Smart Phone era">​</a></h2>
<p>To be able to use internet, we would need a computer. Cybercafé was in the rising. Internet hubs around the corner were occupied throughout. As long as we were in the Internet cafe, we were online, which was usually 1hr per day. This meant we still had an offline life per se. Even though we were always curious to know what happened online, we had to wait until the next day. Smart phones changed it all. Mobile phones which were always used for messaging and calling when turned into smart phones, things changed. We could be connected online 24/7, which in turn changed our mindset. From being accepted online to wanting to be accepted, our perspective changed.</p>
<p>With smartphones and cheap internet, we clicked Refresh every second. Every notification was important. I for one, installed Facebook, twitter, Orkut etc. I tried every application available on the play store. Somehow it made me feel important. With the demand of smartphone market rising, there was a huge competition in the social media applications which in turn lead for them to evolve.</p>
<p>One thing that impressed me about twitter or Facebook was their evolution. The decision makers at these companies were surely great thought leaders. They knew where the trend was. The implementation of infinite scroll in twitter/Facebook and also how they put in thoughts to improve the user experience of the application, impressed me. What they did? They ensured that despite of limited focus/attention of the user, they would glue the user for a longer time on their application.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-addiction">My Addiction<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#my-addiction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My Addiction" title="Direct link to My Addiction">​</a></h2>
<p>I wanted to be the part of the conversation. Be it twitter or Facebook. Every comment was important. Every like was cherished. I waited for #followfriday's. (A twitter trend where users would recommend to their followers, other users who they can follow). It may sound crazy, but all this was so important to me, as if my life dependent on it. Back then, I even wrote articles on why twitter was the best social media application.</p>
<p>Later during the guilt trips, I would console myself thinking that I am learning about various topics, improving my general knowledge. Difficult to digest, but that was the truth.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="happy-realization">Happy Realization<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#happy-realization" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Happy Realization" title="Direct link to Happy Realization">​</a></h2>
<p>Smart phones are boon, no doubt. But unless controlled by massive will power, they can be as good as a nuke. The realization struck me when my life turned havoc. I was not planning things ahead of time, always procrastinating. My priorities were unthought of. Most important, I had sleepless nights and tiring mornings. Things had to change. I had to bring in change to my own life and be able to control my actions.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-minimalist-phone">The minimalist phone<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#the-minimalist-phone" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The minimalist phone" title="Direct link to The minimalist phone">​</a></h2>
<p>First thing first. Delete all the social media accounts. It is very difficult to delete a Facebook account, literally. The delete feature is hidden somewhere below the layers of Facebook, they would ask several questions and wait for couple of weeks before the account is deleted. Meanwhile if you login to some other application via Facebook, your Facebook account is activated back. Smart move Facebook. Whatsoever, I was able to delete my account. I then deleted the Facebook application. similar with twitter, Instagram and other trendy online social media applications. The idea was to clean my smartphone.</p>
<p>Not just social media, I found that the news apps were useless too and contributed to the clutter. The idea was to have minimum screen time. These days smartphones come with such applications by default, so we need to go one step above to deactivate them from the system's settings.</p>
<p>The best option is to deactivate push notifications from each of the apps. No matter what, we don't want any notifications, or alerts etc on our mobile phone. Period.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-about-other-applications">What about other applications?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#what-about-other-applications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What about other applications?" title="Direct link to What about other applications?">​</a></h2>
<p>Yes, there are many applications that you may think are very important to you. Since I was on the path of achieving minimalist phone, my approach was to delete all the third party applications no matter what. Just clean the phone. Don't think about whether you will need it in future. Delete those social media applications, the news apps, the games, online shopping applications like amazon etc.
Done? Yes, Done.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="but-what-about-when-we-really-need-those-applications">But what about when we really need those applications?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#but-what-about-when-we-really-need-those-applications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to But what about when we really need those applications?" title="Direct link to But what about when we really need those applications?">​</a></h2>
<p>Think about it, you never need any application. There is always an alternative.
Want to read news? Open your laptop and go read news.
Want to do online shopping? Again, go to your desktop.
Play games? Ok. But not on your mobile.
Watch videos? YouTube on your desktop.</p>
<p>What about if I really had to use any of the application? Who has stopped you from downloading it? Considering that we are connected 24/7 to internet, the application is just few minutes away from the download. Use it as per your need. Uninstall it again. Repeat in case of emergency.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-a-minimalist-phone">Why a minimalist phone?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#why-a-minimalist-phone" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why a minimalist phone?" title="Direct link to Why a minimalist phone?">​</a></h2>
<p>A minimalist phone keeps you focused, attentive and forces you to speak and communicate with your colleagues and family. We often observe that in a meeting, most of the attendees are deeply immersed in their phone just hitting that refresh button, doing nothing. We take the speaker for granted. Imagine, how would you feel when you are speaking and everyone else is just physically present. You would feel rejected.</p>
<p>Your smart phone is not the only way to stay connected. It is preferred way of staying connected because it involves minimum efforts. However, you miss the heart to heart connection which according to me is an important aspect for building strong relationships.</p>
<p>I have been an advocate of not using social media for a long time now. I use very few applications on my smartphone.</p>
<ul>
<li>Google photos - To keep all my photos synced.</li>
<li>YouTube - Because I follow technical tutorials.</li>
<li>Google podcast - To listen to podcasts on the move.</li>
<li>Google pay - To make digital transactions.</li>
</ul>
<p>I don't have my email configured on the phone. I like to check emails only when I want to.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-am-i-loosing-with-this-minimalism">What am I loosing with this minimalism?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#what-am-i-loosing-with-this-minimalism" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What am I loosing with this minimalism?" title="Direct link to What am I loosing with this minimalism?">​</a></h2>
<p>I don't know what most of my batchmates are doing. I don't know their birthday's and how many kids they have. Does it matter to me? Not really.
Without any news application, I have nearly zero general knowledge. I don't mind. As long as I am involved in something that solves a problem, I am happy to stay away from the paid journalism.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-are-the-advantages">What are the advantages?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/the-minimalist-phone#what-are-the-advantages" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What are the advantages?" title="Direct link to What are the advantages?">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>I feel less distracted</li>
<li>The time that was wasted in browsing online content, I now invest it into creating content. Creating content helps me think. I don't write for others, I write for myself.</li>
<li>I invest time in prototyping my own Ideas. Working on actual ideas help me rate my capability and improve my thinking.</li>
<li>The online drama would mean a lot of negativity. Right now, I wish to stay focused and filter unwanted opinions.</li>
</ul>
<p>I will not speak for or against social media. It has its own advantages. The question is, are we strong enough to understand its need in our lives? Can we justify its presence?</p>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
        <category label="minimalism" term="minimalism"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[A night of coding - Developer chaos]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding"/>
        <updated>2019-08-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[First, a little background. I had an important feature delivery in the coming week but due to personal work, had to take two days off on a short notice. This meant, I had to complete my current development tasks. "No Problemo !", I thought. My inspiration for working overnight comes form the movie, "The Social Network". I have mentioned about how amazing the soundtrack of the movie is, umpteen times, here on this blog. This essay is my retrospection per se on working overnight.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First, a little background. I had an important feature delivery in the coming week but due to personal work, had to take two days off on a short notice. This meant, I had to complete my current development tasks. "No Problemo !", I thought. My inspiration for working overnight comes form the movie, "The Social Network". I have mentioned about how amazing the soundtrack of the movie is, umpteen times, here on this blog. This essay is my retrospection per se on working overnight.</p>
<p>Work commitments of an important feature delivery and family never go in hand. You will spend more time working compared to the time spent with family or honing your hobbies, the universal accepted law for the software professional by the software professional, always holds true.</p>
<p>Due to personal work, I had to take two days off on a very short notice. This meant that I had to complete my current development tasks. The task at hand was doable, however there was a time crunch. The only option I had was to stretch and work overnight. I set a plan of action and put a checklist.</p>
<ul>
<li>Drink black coffee (my favourite)</li>
<li>Listen to the soundtrack of the movie "The social network". (I am listening to it right now while I type this blog post)</li>
<li>Code, debug, repeat.</li>
<li>Log every half hour of my experience</li>
</ul>
<p>With everything in order, I had my mind set to achieve the goal. I put a time check for 10.00 PM, when everyone in the family would be asleep allowing me to work on my tasks.</p>
<p>This post is my retrospection of working overnight. Let the fun begin.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Coffee and Computer" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/computer-and-coffee-46ab5bc6a862f68f2c796153757cee88.jpg" width="500" height="282" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-went-well">What went well?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#what-went-well" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What went well?" title="Direct link to What went well?">​</a></h2>
<p>Everything was planned ahead of time. I had accounted for various tasks and had foreseen blockers. I had a clear picture of the development work that was expected from me. Since my code would be used by the backend team for further execution, I had to ensure that all the test cases were accounted for and taken care of well in advance.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="no-external-distractions">No external distractions<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#no-external-distractions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to No external distractions" title="Direct link to No external distractions">​</a></h3>
<p>I could differentiate clearly the effects of working in an office environment versus working alone. There were no distractions, no small talks and it was peaceful. I could hear the tick of the clock every second, and I loved it. There were zero meetings and no chat messages. As opposing I am of group meetings, I understand that they are important. But when you have a deadline, meetings can be skipped. Working in silence, my concentration skyrocketed.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="extensive-code-comments">Extensive code comments<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#extensive-code-comments" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Extensive code comments" title="Direct link to Extensive code comments">​</a></h3>
<p>I've grown to honour the fact that extensive commenting is a necessity in every line of code that we write. As a developer, I had to re-visit my own code down the line and with a weak memory lane, it was always as good as reading someone else's piece of code. I would struggle. But with extensive commenting, It always becomes easier to deep dive in the codebase.</p>
<p>With clear and distraction free mindset, I spent quality time writing detailed comments. Sometimes, I would comment the flow of what I want to achieve followed by the line of code and sometimes it was vice versa. The point is, I could feel that my thoughts were crystal clear.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ownership">Ownership<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#ownership" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ownership" title="Direct link to Ownership">​</a></h3>
<p>I was independently working on this task and had the complete ownership of it. This meant, I had to ensure that every corner of the testing be completed on time before the delivery.</p>
<p>It could have been the excitement of working overnight or it could be the sense of ownership, but I felt the responsibility of ensuring that I had completed everything on my tasks list.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="end-to-end-testing">End to end testing<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#end-to-end-testing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to End to end testing" title="Direct link to End to end testing">​</a></h3>
<p>I was doing a module that was user facing i.e developing the User interface. There were some API's that were still under development. I did not want to be blocked so I figured a way around. I tried mocking the response signature which then helped me continue in my development. This may sound obvious but sometimes it so happens that some team members want to get all the work ready on which they are dependent instead of mocking their way around.</p>
<p>How did working overnight help me here?
I googled my way around to see if there was any API service that I could use and sure there was, I found mocky. It is simple to use and I could also set delays on the response, which helped me test my loading API. If I had waited for the API, instead of writing this post, I would still be working on my task.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="coffee-and-bourbon">Coffee and Bourbon<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#coffee-and-bourbon" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Coffee and Bourbon" title="Direct link to Coffee and Bourbon">​</a></h3>
<p>I have an affinity towards black coffee. I prepared a cup at my leisure and to add to the icing, I had an entire packet of bourbon (my favourite biscuits) at my disposal. The combination was amazing and it kept me intrigued.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-didnt-go-well">What didn't go well<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#what-didnt-go-well" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What didn't go well" title="Direct link to What didn't go well">​</a></h2>
<p>Nothing can be as perfect as it sounds. Working overnight also had its downsides. Even though it was a planned activity, coding may not always work as expected. Sometimes, a simple semicolon could give you a headache and if you loose patience, solving a tiny bug becomes horrendous.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="distractions">Distractions<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#distractions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Distractions" title="Direct link to Distractions">​</a></h3>
<p>Even though concentration skyrocketed, my coffee breaks ranged between 5 - 15 minutes every 30 minutes. Sometimes I would think about a problem only to realize that I was in some other world of thoughts altogether. It was funny.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="server-restarts-and-cache-deletions">Server restarts and cache deletions<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#server-restarts-and-cache-deletions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Server restarts and cache deletions" title="Direct link to Server restarts and cache deletions">​</a></h3>
<p>Despite of preparation, technical issues always arise. Our applications need a constant server restarts and most of the time when there are JavaScript changes, we need to always clear browser cache. Such tiny tasks take up mundane efforts which eventually lead to frustrations.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Server restarts" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/server-b8b5b20fe167023ffb125127860db659.jpg" width="500" height="239" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="sleep-deprivation">Sleep deprivation<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#sleep-deprivation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Sleep deprivation" title="Direct link to Sleep deprivation">​</a></h3>
<p>At around 2.00 AM, my eyes hurt. I wasn't feeling sleepy, but I wished I was in bed. My train of thoughts, basically it stopped. I could feel the tiredness. I was just half way through my work and it was a sad realization. I then realized that working late nights is not heroic as it sounds.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hacker-news-ftw">Hacker News FTW<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#hacker-news-ftw" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hacker News FTW" title="Direct link to Hacker News FTW">​</a></h3>
<p>To keep working, I visited Hacker News. Somehow I believed that since I was in the middle of the night, the amazing folks at the other side of the globe would be at work and would post some amazing links which would be upvoted and worth a read. In the end, the goal was to keep myself awake.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/night-coding#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>The experience was overall, amazing and at the same time very tiring.</p>
<p>What did I learn?</p>
<ul>
<li>Always finish your tasks on time. Stick to the deadlines.</li>
<li>In your task breakup, account for a buffer time. Due to uncertain circumstances, it may seem impossible to complete a task on a give timeline. You cannot calculate an exact time, but at least have yourself breathing time.</li>
<li>I would definitely not prefer working overnight. The body along with the mind needs a considerable amount of rest. Some of the most successful entrepreneurs may have turned stones into gold working late hours, but we cannot always step in their shoes.</li>
<li>A single night of experience may not be enough to reach to a conclusion. Working late hours was quite an experience. I would not recommend it.</li>
</ul>
<p>What next?</p>
<ul>
<li>I have read and watched numerous videos about waking up at 4.00 AM and getting the maximum work done. I want to be able to try doing that some day. I do have my alarm set to 3.30 AM everyday and there is no shame in hiding the truth, I never was able to get up that early. But some day, I wish to overcome the sleep and set a target. Until I experience it first hand, I wouldn't be able to tell the difference.</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="Essays" term="Essays"/>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I wasted 2hrs debugging my own code]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging"/>
        <updated>2019-07-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Writing code is fun, interesting and fulfilling. However, debugging is an equally important skill. Solving an issue sometimes may give you a taste of hell especially when you are not aware where to look for the root cause. At first, a defect may look simple, but figuring out what to debug and where to hunt demands for attention. Today was a fine morning, after sipping my coffee and afresh, I was sure I would destroy the task at hand point blank. Fate was not on my side and I hit a roadblock. I spent almost 2hrs trying to figure what could possibly go wrong, most of the time starring at the screen clueless. I needed a different perspective.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing code is fun, interesting and fulfilling. However, debugging is an equally important skill. Solving an issue sometimes may give you a taste of hell especially when you are not aware where to look for the root cause. At first, a defect may look simple, but figuring out what to debug and where to hunt demands for attention. Today was a fine morning, after sipping my coffee and afresh, I was sure I would destroy the task at hand point blank. Fate was not on my side and I hit a roadblock. I spent almost 2hrs trying to figure what could possibly go wrong, most of the time starring at the screen clueless. I needed a different perspective.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="background">Background<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#background" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Background" title="Direct link to Background">​</a></h3>
<p>We have a product in which we use <code>.less</code> to write our styles. Being a dojo/dijit integration, it already has many .less files in its theme. We then made our custom theme and created our own <code>.less</code> files which are then eventually converted to a single <code>.css</code> file.</p>
<p>My task at hand was to delete all the code that was written specifically for IE6 browser. Dojo adds a browser specific class to body which can then be used to target styles for that browser. I had to delete code. Easy. I love the delete button on my keyboard.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-setup">The Setup<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#the-setup" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Setup" title="Direct link to The Setup">​</a></h3>
<p>Visual Studio Code is my primary code editor and I used <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=mrcrowl.easy-less" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Easy LESS extension</a> to Auto-compile LESS to CSS on save. It worked really well.
Every time I saved a change in my <code>.less</code> file, it would show an indication in the status bar about the time required to convert the <code>.less</code> to <code>.css</code></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Visual Studio status bar message" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/vscode-status-message-cc45498c662da30df3d55bdfc56b9b59.jpg" width="500" height="454" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-happened-today">What Happened today<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#what-happened-today" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What Happened today" title="Direct link to What Happened today">​</a></h3>
<p>I started deleting most obvious lines of code which I was pretty confident. I hit the ctrl+s to save my changes and then I opened my main<code>.less</code> file to compile all the changes throughout project. <code>main.less</code> basically has all the imports from various other files. For. eg import of button.less and <code>color.less</code> and so on. So after every change in a particular file, I had to compile <code>main.less</code> to get the final <code>.css</code> output.</p>
<p>Today, when I saved the changes, I was expecting to see the compilation successful message. To my surprise, the editor message stuck to "Compiling LESS to CSS". I waited a longer but in vain.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="debug-mistake---looking-at-the-wrong-place">Debug mistake - Looking at the wrong place<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#debug-mistake---looking-at-the-wrong-place" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Debug mistake - Looking at the wrong place" title="Direct link to Debug mistake - Looking at the wrong place">​</a></h3>
<p>Since the changes were not reflecting, I was not sure where to look for.
I did not see any compilation error messages on the screen nor on the debug console or terminal or anything on the problems tab. Strange.</p>
<p>I thought there was some issue with compiler.</p>
<ul>
<li>I restarted my editor. It did not work</li>
<li>I then re-installed the Easy LESS extension, still it did not work</li>
<li>I remembered that we are using a special setting for compilation, i.e we are using relativeURL in our .less code, so I changed the settings. I saved the main.less file again and still it was stuck at the message.</li>
<li>I then reverted the changes and it was of no use.</li>
</ul>
<p>After following several trial and error attempts, I decided to discard the extension and look for another extension in the VS Code Marketplace. There, I found Easy Compile. I tried installing it, but this time the compilation would not work. I did not see any status message. Perhaps it needed some settings.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="loosing-patience">Loosing patience<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#loosing-patience" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Loosing patience" title="Direct link to Loosing patience">​</a></h3>
<p>I then deleted the Easy Compile extension and restored back to Easy LESS extension. I had used this extension several times and I desperately wanted to get it working. I lost patience.</p>
<p>I had to take break. I was already an hour and half doing stupid activities.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-problem">The problem<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#the-problem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The problem" title="Direct link to The problem">​</a></h3>
<p>I then looked with a fresh mind. At first I had concluded that the problem was with the compiler. I had to rethink my approach. Since the <code>main.less</code> has imports of various different .less files, I deleted the entire code in it and saved my changes.</p>
<p>To my surprise, the compilation message was successful. It returned an empty <code>main.css</code> file. The error was in the code. But where?</p>
<p>It hit me like a lightning bolt. I had made changes to the code. But why was I not getting any error message? I then realized, the file which I was compiling was different compared to the file which had error.</p>
<p>Also, the file in which I deleted that said variable compiled successfully. However the file which was using that variable had not been triggered for compilation. Hence no error logged. And that is why the main.less compilation was stuck.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-solution">The Solution<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#the-solution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Solution" title="Direct link to The Solution">​</a></h3>
<p>I did a global search for the variable in question, deleted all the instances of it and compiled each file. I then compiled main.less file and got the final <code>.css</code> file. A lesson learned.</p>
<p>Below is how the error message appears on failed compilation.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Visual Studio Status Error message" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/vscode-status-errormessage-69408ece7b5c1a5d83fe0043043c9deb.jpg" width="614" height="258" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h3>
<p>I learned very important lesson</p>
<ul>
<li>Do not debug a issue based on wild guess and assumptions</li>
<li>Try to replicate the issue by making dramatic changes in the code. Observe if your changes lead to a better conclusion. For eg. In my main.less file, I deleted all the imports which should create at least a blank <code>.css</code> file. Since it created a blank <code>.css</code> file, I was at least assured that the compiler worked fine.</li>
<li>Test the positive scenarios to get an understanding of the code. Observe the pattern of how the code worked before making any changes.</li>
<li>Make obvious changes to the code to see if you are in the correct file. For example, introduce an alert or a debugger statement. This will ensure that you are making changes in the correct file.</li>
<li>Do not debug an issue on guess work. For example, by making code changes in a file that has similar name as the UI module you are trying to fix debug. This will only waste your debug efforts. Identify the correct source code file beforehand.</li>
<li>Re-installing the software and re-starting the computer should be the last option. Literally.</li>
<li>Be patient. Software does not work on hope and luck. Understand that software is written based on logic and algorithm and hence every output that you see on the screen has a base.</li>
</ul>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ps">P.S<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/wasterd-2hrs-debugging#ps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to P.S" title="Direct link to P.S">​</a></h4>
<p>I had faced this same issue earlier around a year back. I did remember this but I could not recollect how I got my way through that time. I am documenting this experience for I know I would need it somewhere in the future. Also, I hope this helps someone on the interwebs.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="debugging" term="debugging"/>
        <category label="learnings" term="learnings"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advice I would give myself If I were in College]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self"/>
        <updated>2019-06-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Computer science is the most sought for specialization in Engineering colleges, at least that's what I've heard. When I entered my first year of college, I barely knew that Computer science means theoretical study of computers. Even though we had the best of the syllabus, I could hardly relate the theoretical knowledge with the practical world. Despite of having practical hands-on sessions on almost every subject which I think constituted 20% to 30% of the time we spent in the entire course, I found it difficult to understand the concepts. This was around 12 years back.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Computer science is the most sought for specialization in Engineering colleges, at least that's what I've heard. When I entered my first year of college, I barely knew that Computer science means theoretical study of computers. Even though we had the best of the syllabus, I could hardly relate the theoretical knowledge with the practical world. Despite of having practical hands-on sessions on almost every subject which I think constituted 20% to 30% of the time we spent in the entire course, I found it difficult to understand the concepts. This was around 12 years back.</p>
<p>Assuming that the current curriculum consists of theoretical knowledge, how can one outperform in college? After having a decade of experience, I try to explore and answer the question, <em>"what advice would I give myself if I were back in college?"</em></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="so-what-is-it-that-changes-now">So what is it that changes now?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#so-what-is-it-that-changes-now" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to So what is it that changes now?" title="Direct link to So what is it that changes now?">​</a></h3>
<p>Resources. Period. We have easy access to Smartphones and every house has a good configuration laptop. However, the most decisive factor is availability of super high speed internet. Around a decade ago, personal computers were a dream and internet was costly. Did you know? We used dial-up connection.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="advice-i-would-give-myself-if-i-were-in-college">Advice I would give myself If I were in college?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#advice-i-would-give-myself-if-i-were-in-college" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Advice I would give myself If I were in college?" title="Direct link to Advice I would give myself If I were in college?">​</a></h3>
<p>This essay is a retrospection to my Academic and Professional journey so far. I am still a student, learning everyday and trying to keep up with latest technologies. Considering that we have easily available resources, I want to write them here not just for me, but for anyone who reads this post.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="1-enjoy-your-college-life">1. Enjoy your college life<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#1-enjoy-your-college-life" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Enjoy your college life" title="Direct link to 1. Enjoy your college life">​</a></h3>
<p>Enjoy every second of your college, make new friends and learn everyday. Most important, make mistakes and learn from them. Improve. While in college, you are not liable to anyone but you. Be Responsible. College is where you can shape your career. Make memories.
P.S Most important, take photos, make videos. Have Fun.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Enjoy College" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/Enjoy-College-dbeb96b3130cc8dfd0e00792e5f5c5c5.jpg" width="800" height="462" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2-read">2. Read<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#2-read" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Read" title="Direct link to 2. Read">​</a></h3>
<p>Read, technical books, fiction, dramas etc. At-least half-hour daily. How will that help?</p>
<ul>
<li>With consistent reading, you will improve your vocabulary.</li>
<li>You will learn to speed-read, and in turn, you will understand and remember what you read for a longer period of time.</li>
<li>Reading wide range of topics will give you perspective. You will question things and sought answer to them.</li>
<li>Reading will boost your creativity.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Reading" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/Reading-086dae0104b483ec31130470a3ce238f.jpg" width="800" height="470" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="3-participate-and-contribute">3. Participate and Contribute<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#3-participate-and-contribute" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Participate and Contribute" title="Direct link to 3. Participate and Contribute">​</a></h3>
<p>In this era of social media, instead of <del>wasting</del> utilizing your time in social media like Facebook, Instagram, participate in communities like stack overflow.</p>
<h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-stackoverflow">a. StackOverflow:<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#a-stackoverflow" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to a. StackOverflow:" title="Direct link to a. StackOverflow:">​</a></h5>
<p>Stack overflow is a reputed and highly visited (top 140 websites) community of developers who help each other to solve technical problems. You can build a good reputation on Stack overflow which will boost your career. StackOverflow has gamified their software, one gets rewarded for asking questions and most importantly answering to other people's posts. You get rewarded for correcting questions/answers too. With consistency, over the course of time, your profile will be evident to companies seeking for technically strong candidates.</p>
<h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="b-open-source">b. Open source:<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#b-open-source" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to b. Open source:" title="Direct link to b. Open source:">​</a></h5>
<p>Contribute to open source projects on GitHub. Create your profile on GitHub and publish your own projects or fork interesting projects and contribute to them. Do not hesitate to publish your source code online. As long as you are disciplined and consistent, pushing your code on GitHub will give you good exposure. But what will you push to GitHub? You can</p>
<ul>
<li>Solve Hacker Rank/LeetCode challenges and publish your solution in GitHub</li>
<li>Work on simple projects like a Calculator, Birthday Reminder, Invoice generation, Web scrapper etc. Create such projects in different technologies like python, c++, JavaScript etc.</li>
</ul>
<h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="c-mooc-massive-open-online-course">c. MOOC (Massive open online course):<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#c-mooc-massive-open-online-course" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to c. MOOC (Massive open online course):" title="Direct link to c. MOOC (Massive open online course):">​</a></h5>
<p>MOOC are the next big thing. With plethora of online courses and with amazing instructors, try and complete as many interesting courses as possible. There are many websites like Coursera, EdX, Udemy etc. that provide good courses. The most important and the best part in participating and completing them is that you will get certificate. This will boost your profile. If you complete your course, you receive badges which you can publish on LinkedIn, your personal blog or any social media.</p>
<h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="d-freecodecamp">d. FreeCodeCamp<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#d-freecodecamp" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to d. FreeCodeCamp" title="Direct link to d. FreeCodeCamp">​</a></h5>
<p><a href="https://www.freecodecamp.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">FreeCodeCamp</a> is yet another MOOC, however it has thousands of exercise on front-end development. I found it real helpful to master technologies such as HTML, CSS and JavaScript. There are various inspirational stories on internet about how FreeCodeCamp helped someone get a good job. Having used it extensively, I can vouch for this platform. Not to forget, the certificate is completely free.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="4-build-a-brand">4. Build a Brand<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#4-build-a-brand" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. Build a Brand" title="Direct link to 4. Build a Brand">​</a></h3>
<p>Create and Publish. Be Visible. Build a Brand. College is when you can invest your time in creative things. A brand is an identity through which everyone recognizes you. As a software engineer, what can you do?</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Build a Brand" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/Build-Brand-526ea779d07fbf494ef11758d4d2f172.jpg" width="800" height="450" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-create-your-personal-webpage">a. Create your personal webpage.<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#a-create-your-personal-webpage" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to a. Create your personal webpage." title="Direct link to a. Create your personal webpage.">​</a></h5>
<p>Did you know, you can create and host a webpage completely for free? There are many hosting services, but I would insist upon GitHub. With GitHub pages, you can create and host a static webpage. Apart from GitHub being completely free, another advantage is that if you consistently push your code to GitHub, it shows how passionate you are about open source, code commits, technology etc. All your projects and open source activities will be discoverable via GitHub.</p>
<h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="b-write-blog">b. Write. Blog.<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#b-write-blog" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to b. Write. Blog." title="Direct link to b. Write. Blog.">​</a></h5>
<p>Just as Reading is important, so is Writing.</p>
<p>What to write? Where to write?</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Blog</strong> : Maintaining an online log (blog) is beneficial. Writing helps you pen down your thoughts in a clear and concise manner. This means that you will be able to communicate better. In your job, you will be constantly writing emails, attending scrum meetings and writing requirement documents. Your habit of writing blog will help you better communicate your thoughts to the readers/managers/colleagues.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Where to Blog?</strong> : You can use blogger, WordPress etc blogging services, but I would insists on using Jekyll instead. As long as you write consistently, it does not matter what blogging platform you are using.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>What to Blog?</strong> : Blog your thoughts. Everything. I was inspired by the movie "The Social Network", when Mark Z. blogs about how he wishes to divert his mind and that he needs an idea. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BPazh2kDdvA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Remember</a>? P.S : I am not promoting that you write about your girlfriend, but you get the gist.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Writing" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/Writing-7fbba7f42d7a3e4086c57c1b12b8e765.jpg" width="800" height="399" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Let's say you learn about some cool technology, you can write about what you learned from it. You can write about movie reviews or an idea that you want to pursue. Again, Blog your thoughts. My advice of writing everything under the sky is debatable.</p>
<p>Some industry experts would say that, it is always better to write about topics that interest you and stick to the niche. You can then build an audience around your topic of expertise. For eg, if you write about fashion, do not write movie reviews. If you talk about technology, do not write about cooking. Yes, it is wise to stick to a niche topic, but hear me out. You are a student in college which means you would be just starting to explore blogging. Thus, being a beginner, you will want to learn about, what blogging is? How to promote yourself? What are analytics? What is SEO? etc. The answer to all these questions you will learn on the go. Consistency is the key.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>"Ok ok, I am sold. Anything else?"</strong> : Hell yes! I missed the most important point. Besides improving your communication, vocabulary, creating an internet presence and overall growing intellectually, blogging will help you improve your typing speed. I am a huge advocate of using the keyboard without looking at it. Advantages? First of all, you will type faster, much accurate. Second, you will save a lot of time, you just need to look at the screen when you type. If you spent time looking at the keyboard searching for the right keys, you will then spend time on the screen to find typo. Twice the time utilised.</li>
</ul>
<p>I have to quote <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/09/programmings-dirtiest-little-secret.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Steve Yegge</a> on the use of keyboard here. He summarises the importance of using keyboard bull's eye.</p>
<p>"I can't understand why professional programmers out there allow themselves to have a career without teaching themselves to type. It doesn't make any sense. It's like being, I dunno, an actor without knowing how to put your clothes on. It's showing up to the game unprepared. It's coming to a meeting without your slides. Going to class without your homework. Swimming in the Olympics wearing a pair of Eddie Bauer Adventurer Shorts."</p>
<p>There are many games, that improve your typing skills. I encourage that you play once in a while those games.</p>
<p>P.S : Look at your keyboard and touch the "F" and "J" keys. Do you feel anything different when comparing to any other keys on the keyboard? Go figure.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="5-networking">5. Networking<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#5-networking" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. Networking" title="Direct link to 5. Networking">​</a></h3>
<p>College is the best time to get involved. These days, there are many meetup's held to help students learn various technologies. Attend such meetups. Not only you will learn about the latest and the greatest but you will also learn about individuals. Try to follow the "SME's (Subject Matter Expert's) on social media or look at their open source repositories. Usually, these SME's are professionals with many years of hands-on experience.</p>
<p>During meetups, share ideas, listen to the advocates, build a professional network. LinkedIn is the best web application that you can develop your professional network online. Make use of it extensively.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="6-side-projects-hobby-projects">6. Side Projects/ Hobby Projects<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#6-side-projects-hobby-projects" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 6. Side Projects/ Hobby Projects" title="Direct link to 6. Side Projects/ Hobby Projects">​</a></h3>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Hobby Projects" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/Hobby-Projects-7c6ceb2c98809fb3f964b407e9225edb.jpg" width="800" height="424" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>I cannot stress more on the importance of Side Projects. Side projects are usually something that you do out of hobby apart from your daily routine. Being into the field of technology, a hobby project would be like <em>implementing an automated feed reader</em> or <em>creating a mobile application that notifies you about a quote daily in the morning</em>. Sky is the limit. Usually a side project is to bring into life an idea that you think will be useful to you. Sometimes, you find certain technology interesting which you want to explore. The best way to learn it would be to work on a project. Reading through tutorials and articles would just give your theoretical knowledge, but actual implementation and getting your hands dirty would teach you the technology.</p>
<p>When working on hobby projects, ensure that you have a demo of your work hosted somewhere online. When someone visits your profile, it is always good to show a MVP (Minimal Viable Product) of your project.</p>
<p>"I know Flutter" v/s "I've made X using Flutter". Which statement do you think makes more impact?</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="7-list-of-useful-links-and-webapps">7. List of Useful Links and WebApps.<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#7-list-of-useful-links-and-webapps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 7. List of Useful Links and WebApps." title="Direct link to 7. List of Useful Links and WebApps.">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://github.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a> : To host your code samples, build a static web page etc. <a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Getting-Started-What-is-Git%3F" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Git is the most widely used version control system</a>. Just as how important learning a programming language is, so is important to be familiar with Git.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://stackoverflow.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">StackOverflow</a> : is the largest, most trusted online community for anyone that codes to learn, share their knowledge, and build their careers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/steveyegge2/you-should-write-blogs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">You should write Blogs</a> : A good article which inspired me to write my blog. This was published in the year 2005, but it is relevant till date.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://johnresig.com/blog/write-code-every-day/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write Code Everyday</a> : Since the beginning of my career, I was highly inspired by JQuery Javascript Library and read a lot about its creator, John Resig. One of the blog post, "Write Code Everyday" by John Resig keeps me motivated. I have tried several times and having failed at it miserably, somewhere down I know that this is a good practice I need to force myself to keep up. I would urge that you read the article and inculcate it in your routine.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HackerNews</a> : Hacker News is user submitted high quality technical articles for exchanging news and sharing views. The articles shared are of high quality, so are the comments. Unlike any social media, hacker news is clean, clutter free and has top rated and upvoted articles.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Paul Graham Essays</a> : When I discovered Hacker News, I learned about YCombinator and Paul Graham. I learned about how the best of the best technology companies and their products are backed by YCombinator. I wanted to learn more and then I discovered inspiring essays by Paul Graham. One of them was <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/hp.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hackers and Painters</a>. Paul Graham's insights into StartUp world and his advice out of his experience are amazing to read and learn from.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CodingHorror</a> : Jeff AtWood's blog posts are insightful. Being a huge fan of StackOverflow, I had to learn about Jeff AtWood and Joel Spolsky who founded StackOverflow.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/we-are-typists-first-programmers-second/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">We are Typist first, Programmers Second</a> and <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/09/programmings-dirtiest-little-secret.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Programming's Dirtiest Little Secret</a> : These are gems worth reading.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/08/09/the-joel-test-12-steps-to-better-code/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">12 Steps to Better Code</a> : This article by Joel Spolsky has been quoted on various websites. It is worth bookmarking.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="disciplin-is-the-key">Disciplin is the Key<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/advice-to-self#disciplin-is-the-key" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Disciplin is the Key" title="Direct link to Disciplin is the Key">​</a></h3>
<p>If you look at the right resources and follow the right technology enthusiasts, you will learn a lot. Internet being so vast, it is common to get distracted and drifted. The click-baits and the recommendation engine to be blamed here. I use YouTube to learn various things and many times I get distracted by the recommendation engine and click on another video without completing the one I started on the first place.</p>
<p>Thus the most important advice I would give myself is to be disciplined. If you pick a task, finish it in one seating. Don't get distracted or diverted and do not procrastinate. Make a ToDo list and keep a track on hourly basis. Maintain a daily log of what you achieved and what went wrong throughout the day. Keep a positive attitude and always acknowledge your own actions.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="advice" term="advice"/>
        <category label="learnings" term="learnings"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things learned in 10 years of Experience as a Software Engineer]]></title>
        <id>https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences</id>
        <link href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences"/>
        <updated>2019-06-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am a avid reader of HackerNews, I like to read about start-ups and I love to work with code. I started my career as a programmer working on web projects. I have had experiences working independently and with a huge team. In this post, I try to pen down my experiences as a software developer and some of the things I learned throughout this journey.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am a avid reader of HackerNews, I like to read about start-ups and I love to work with code. I started my career as a programmer working on web projects. I have had experiences working independently and with a huge team. In this post, I try to pen down my experiences as a software developer and some of the things I learned throughout this journey.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="continuous-learning">Continuous learning<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences#continuous-learning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Continuous learning" title="Direct link to Continuous learning">​</a></h3>
<p>At first continuous learning sounds super daunting, but once you fall in love with the challenging problems and go on a quest to find optimal solution, you start enjoying. If you think the learning phase is up to graduation/post-graduation, then you are mistaken. A programmer will never stop learning. There will always be new technology out there which you may have to learn to keep up with your job and compete in this industry. A dormant, not-ready to upgrade their skills programmer will soon fall behind and will be left alone. It is as it sounds, cruel. But if you enjoy reading and learning about new technical fundamentals and you look forward to implementing what you learned, you will feel at home. What you learned today may not be applicable tomorrow, but if you can learn to appreciate this fact and accept the bitter sweet truth, then throughout your journey, every step you take will compound to the glory tomorrow or someday.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="be-patient-and-understand-the-reason-why-the-code-was-written">Be patient and understand the reason why the code was written<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences#be-patient-and-understand-the-reason-why-the-code-was-written" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Be patient and understand the reason why the code was written" title="Direct link to Be patient and understand the reason why the code was written">​</a></h3>
<p>When working in a team, do not judge the code written by your peers. I know of colleagues who constantly complain about some code that was written a long time ago  and how inefficient and vague it was. Rather than complain, my approach has always been to read carefully and understand how the legacy code works, try to figure out the bad parts and fix them. Sometimes a trivial piece of code which may appear to be useless to you may serve a very important purpose. Make sure before making any changes, proper due diligence is carried out.</p>
<p>If you think a piece of code can be improved, by all means go ahead, modify it. These days everyone uses code repository tools that keep track of the history of code changes. sometimes your code change may boost performance of your application, and sometimes it may break a functionality. By all means, make changes to the code if you feel so. We have peer reviews, QA team and product managers and leads to verify the changes and approve.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="always-practice-work-on-side-projects">Always practice, work on side projects<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences#always-practice-work-on-side-projects" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Always practice, work on side projects" title="Direct link to Always practice, work on side projects">​</a></h3>
<p>Practice your trade all the time. Try to work on an idea and create a side project. If you don't have an idea to work on, contribute to open source projects. You can also practice algorithm challenges on Hacker rank, Leetcode etc. Working on side projects opens up your perspective towards programming. Apart from your daily job, You have to discipline yourself and be consistent so as to complete your side projects. At times it becomes extremely difficult to squeeze in some time, but if you force yourself to a tiny commit on GitHub, you will be victorious. Again, all such activities compound to give you greater results over time. Side projects can be anything, and does not always have to be related to your career. If you have a hobby to paint, cook, write blogs, edit videos or make gaming videos, by all means, invest your time and energy in them.
The creator of Jquery, John Resig has a very important essay on his blog about the importance of Writing code everyday. Read it at <a href="https://johnresig.com/blog/write-code-every-day/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write code everyday - By John Resig</a></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pen-down-your-experiences">Pen down your Experiences<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences#pen-down-your-experiences" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Pen down your Experiences" title="Direct link to Pen down your Experiences">​</a></h3>
<p>The best way to remember a programming concept is to teach? Teaching does not mean you need a classroom full of students to get started. You can very well start by creating YouTube videos, or write technical blog posts and share on social media. Sometimes you may not know even the simplest of the things that you thought you were expert at, and it should not bring you down. Try to write a technical post about it while you research and learn more about it. You can write your own coding examples or explain the concept in a simpler language, this will not only help you, but it will also help those reading your article. And in case you need to revisit this technical concept in future, you know where to look for.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Lessons of a Software Engineer" src="https://codingbbq.github.io/assets/images/things-learned-as-software-engineer-ff165b7b945f0b63024d599d7c55e048.jpg" width="800" height="533" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="this-is-not-my-domain-of-expertise">This is not my domain of expertise<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences#this-is-not-my-domain-of-expertise" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to This is not my domain of expertise" title="Direct link to This is not my domain of expertise">​</a></h3>
<p>If you are working on a project and face any issues, instead of assuming that the issue is not related to your domain of expertise, try to backtrack and figure out the solution first before giving up. You may not know the programming language, but with some logic and understanding, you will be able to figure out how the code works. This will help narrow down the issue. And when you need to ask for help, you will be able to pin point and save time.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="stackoverflow-google-to-the-rescue">StackOverflow, Google to the rescue?<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences#stackoverflow-google-to-the-rescue" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to StackOverflow, Google to the rescue?" title="Direct link to StackOverflow, Google to the rescue?">​</a></h3>
<p>For programming related queries, Stack Overflow is THE go to place for every programmer. Chances that your query has already been answered are always high. However sometimes, you many not find the exact solution but then there might be a solution that is close to what you need. So read carefully all the suggestions. Do not hurry asking a question. Also, when you ask a question on Stack overflow, make sure to create a Proof of concept online on site like codepen etc. so that you narrow down the problem you are trying to solve. Anyone who wishes to help will not have to recreate the issue and will have a demo of what exactly you are trying to ask. Also mention what all you have already tried to solve the problem, so that it saves time of anyone who wants to help you.</p>
<p>The clear you are in asking your questions the higher the chances of you receiving an answer.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="be-a-user-first-then-be-a-software-developer">Be a user first, then be a Software developer<a href="https://codingbbq.github.io/blog/ten-years-experiences#be-a-user-first-then-be-a-software-developer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Be a user first, then be a Software developer" title="Direct link to Be a user first, then be a Software developer">​</a></h3>
<p>Have you come across a software that you had the hardest time figuring out how it worked? Even a simple task would require a mundane amount of efforts? The reason being, not your ability to understand the software but the overlooking of the software developer who designed the software. Sometimes, an UI functionality to a software engineer would not be worthy of the efforts, but it may be a huge value addition to the end user. Always try to see a software from the perspective of the user. Try to understand how the User Experience can be improved because in the end, we develop a software to make life of the users easier. We want to usually automate the boring stuff. Right? The best way to see how the software would appeal to anyone is to help them walk through the process and the User Interface designs.</p>
<hr>
<p>This post cannot be concluded, there are so many golden nuggets that I can think of which needs a their own space. As a software engineer in this industry, the lessons I learn everyday are amazing. I cherish this journey and hence, I plan to continue on this series of post someday in future. I would love to hear about your journey. Please feel free to send me an email at codingbbq [@] gmail [dot] com</p>]]></content>
        <category label="personal" term="personal"/>
        <category label="software" term="software"/>
        <category label="experience" term="experience"/>
    </entry>
</feed>